A Guide to the Wright Family papers, 1878-1987
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Wright Family papers, 1878-1987
The Library of Virginia
43567
3.5 cu. ft. (13 boxes and 1 oversize folder)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Two boxes (Box 11-12) of privacy protected records are closed for 75 years from date of creation (includes confidential case histories, employment, and medical records).
Acquisition Information
Gift of Robert A.S. Wright on December 2007 and November 2008, Blacksburg.
Biographical Information
The Wright family were residents of Manchester, (South) Richmond, Virginia, and had several family members serve with the Richmond Police Department. Alexander Steel Wright was born 1 July 1868 in Manchester, Virginia. He was first appointed a police officer with the Manchester Police Commission in 1894, rising to the rank of Captain of Detectives in 1917. He was married to Roberta Gertrude Turner and died in 1945.
John M. Wright Jr. was born 25 April 1901 in Manchester, Virginia, to Alexander Steel Wright and Roberta Gertrude Turner Wright. He married Mary Beatrice Tuma in Washington, D.C., on 27 June 1922. Wright started with the Richmond Police Department February 1920, named Acting Chief March 1960, and became Chief of Police in February 1961. He served until December 1967 and died in 1968. His son, Frank A.S. Wright (1924-1996) was a Circuit Court judge in Richmond.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1878-1987, of the Wright family of Richmond, Virginia. Included are certificates, clippings, correspondence, photographs, programs, and publications documenting their lives and work for the Richmond Police Department. The bulk of the collection relate to Captain Alexander S. Wright, Chief of Detectives, John M. Wright, Chief of Police, and Frank A.S. Wright, Circuit Court judge, all of Richmond.
Included are Annual Reports of the Dept. of Public Safety for the City of Richmond, 1907-1955; Roster and Description of the Police Force City of Richmond, 1878-1885; and memoranda from the City of Richmond Police Department. Also included are congratulatory, recommendation, and condolence letters to John M. Wright from Thomas P. Bryan, J. Edgar Hoover, Charles G. Thalhimer, and George C. Wallace. Of note are the numerous photographs, ca. 1900-1960, from the Richmond Police Department of Alexander S. and John M. Wright, street scenes, panoramic group photographs of policemen, and dedications and banquets.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Papers, 1878-1987
Series II: Photographs, ca. 1890-1971
Series III: Audio/Visual materials, ca. 1968
Contents List
- Series I: Papers, 1878-1987., Extent: 1.65 cu. ft. (5 boxes). (Box 1-5)
  This series, 1878-1987, including birth and wedding announcements, certificates, clippings, correspondence, programs, and publications documenting the Wright family of Richmond, Virginia. The bulk of the collection relate to Captain Alexander S. Wright, Chief of Detectives, and John M. Wright, Chief of Police in Richmond. Also included are papers relating to Frank A.S. Wright, Circuit Court judge in Richmond.
  The papers of Alexander S. Wright and John M. Wright mainly relate to their careers with the Richmond Police Department. Included are blank police department applications, job appointments and certificates, identification cards, curriculum of the Police Academy training school, training manual for the Department of Safety Bureau of Fire, and memoranda from the City of Richmond. Of note are biographies of Alexander and John Wright. Newspaper clippings are included for Alexander, Frank, and John Wright documenting their legal and police careers.
  Topics of Alexander S. Wright's correspondence, 1917-1943, include clarification of laws, letters of appraisal of Wright's work, birthday greetings, and establishment of a victory garden, 1943. John M. Wright's correspondence, 1946-1968, includes congratulatory, retirement, and condolence letters, invitations, and letters of recommendation. Included are letters of recommendation for the Chief of Police job and letters of congratulations when Wright got the job. Correspondents include Mayor Thomas P. Bryan, J. Edgar Hoover, Walter B. Gentry, R. Westwood Winfree, Archer A. Page, W.W. Satterwhite, George C. Wallace, Frank Soden, John B. Tansey, Henry Schwarzschild, James J. Kilpatrick, Thomas J. Bliley, Edward E. Haddock, Charles G. Thalhimer, and James J. Rowley.
  Included are programs and articles relating to Manchester; memorial books from the funerals of Alan S. Wright (1977) and Robert T. Wright (1954); newsletters from The Richmond Employees Bulletin (1955) and Henrico Herald (1967); and obituaries. Also included are programs from the Virginia Police Association convention (1939), Basic Police School graduation program (1966), John M. Wright retirement dinner (1968), and the Police-Fireman baseball game (1969). Of note is the Roster and Description of the Police Force City of Richmond, 1878-1885. Included are names of policemen, rank, age, height, date, married status, where born, former occupation, residence, first appointment, when promoted, and remarks. Also includes lists of policemen first and second class.
  Publications include The National Police Journal, Virginia Police Journal, and The Richchap. Also included is the Annual Report of the Chief of Police Richmond (1907), Classification in the Virginia Penal System (1950), and Annual Reports from the Dept. of Safety of the City of Richmond (1919-1955).
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title with publications arranged to the rear.
  - Announcements, Mr. and Mrs. Carter Douglas Maag, 1943. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Announcements, Frank A.S. Wright, 1961-1964. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Application for the Police Service [blank], nd. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Appointments, John M. Wright, 1926, 1928. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Biography of Alexander S. Wright, ca. 1940. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Biography of John M. Wright, ca. 1967. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Cemetery records, Wright family, 1913-1945. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Certificates, Alexander S. Wright, 1955. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Certificates, Frank A.S. Wright, 1968-1979. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Certificates, John M. Wright, 1961-1968. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Certificates, John M. Wright, Oversize 1956-1967. (Box 5)
  - Clippings, Alexander S. Wright, 1910-1940. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, Frank A.S. Wright, 1967-1984. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Clippings, Frederick B. Wright, Jr., nd. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Clippings, John M. Wright, Jr., 1951. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Clippings, John M. Wright, Jr., 1960-1963. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Clippings, John M. Wright, Jr., 1965. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Clippings, John M. Wright, Jr., 1966. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Clippings, John M. Wright, Jr., 1967. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Clippings, John M. Wright, Jr., 1968. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Clippings, John M. Wright, Jr., 1969-1970. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Clippings, John M. Wright, Jr., nd. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Clippings, John M. Wright Jr. scrapbook, 1967-1968. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Clippings, John M. Wright, Jr., ca. 1950. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Clippings, Miscellaneous, ca. 1937. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Clippings (complete newspapers), 1937-1945. (Box 4)
    The Richmond News Leader Bicentennial Issue (1737-1937), Richmond Times Dispatch (9/8/1937, 5/7/1945, 5/8/1945)
  - Correspondence, Alexander S. Wright, 1917-1943. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, Frank A.S. Wright, 1983-1987. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, John M. Wright, 1946-1960. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, John M. Wright, 1961. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, John M. Wright, 1962-1968. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, Letter to the Evening Dispatch, nd. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, Mayor Henry A. Maurice (copy), 1906. (Box 1, Folder 30a)
  - Fire Bureau Running Book (Richmond), ca. 1950-1960. (Box 1, Folder 30b)
  - Identification cards, Alexander S. Wright, 1939. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Identification cards and wallet, John M. Wright, 1957-1968. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Identification cards, Richard P. Wright, 1973. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Jokes, sayings, poems of Frank A.S. Wright, 1968-1977. (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Manchester, Virginia, 1982-1985. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Memorial book, Alan S. Wright, 1977. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Memorial book, Robert T. Wright, 1954. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Memos, City of Richmond Police Department, 1921-1984. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous, Frank A.S. Wright, 1980-1985. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Newsletters, 1955-1967. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Obituaries, Wright family, 1921-1971. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Poems, John M. Wright, 1967-1968. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Programs, 1939. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    14th Annual Convention of the Virginia Police Executives Association. Includes oversize panoramic photograph of Virginia Police Executives Association, Hotel Chamberlin, 20-21 September 1939 (Photograph is located in oversize cabinet [LVA Lab# 10_1041_001]).
  - Programs, 1941. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Inaugural Ball in Honor of Harry S. Truman
  - Programs, 1966-1969. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Graduation Basic Police School (1966), Retirement Dinner in Honor of John M. Wright (1968), Program 14th Annual Police-Firemen Baseball Game (1969)
  - Richmond Bureau of Police Academy Curriculum, 1968. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Roster and Description of the Police Force City of Richmond, 1878-1885. (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook (oversize), 1941-1945. (Box 5)
  - Speeches, Alexander S. Wright, 1938. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Speeches, nd. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Traffic ticket, 1935. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Publications, Bureau of Police (Richmond), The Citizen and The Police in Crime Prevention, ca. 1961-1967. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Publications, Bureau of Police (Richmond), Fiscal Report of Bureau of Police, 1960-1961. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Publications, Bureau of Police (Richmond), Souvenir History Richmond Police Department, Illustrated, 1901. (Box 3)
  - Publications, Bureau of Police (Richmond), Summary of Activities, 1965 July-1966 June. (Box 3)
  - Publications, Dept. of Corrections (California), Manual of Criminal Statistics, 1950. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Publications, Dept. of Public Safety, Annual Reports of the Chief of Police, 1907. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Publications, Dept. of Public Safety, Annual Reports of the City of Richmond, 1919, 1922, 1928-1930, 1932, 1934-1941, 1944-1945, 1954-1955. (Box 3)
  - Publications, Dept. of Public Safety, Bureau of Fire training manual, 1955. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Publications, Division of Corrections, Classification in the Virginia Penal System, 1950. (Box 4)
  - Publications, FBI Law Enforcement Bulletin (Vol. 34, No. 3), 1965 March. (Box 4)
  - Publications, LAPD Annual Report, 1965. (Box 4)
  - Publications, The National Police Journal (Vol. 50, No. 3), 1967. (Box 4)
  - Publications, The Richchap, 1920 February. (Box 4)
  - Publications, Virginia Police Journal, 1966-1968. (Box 4)
  - Exhibition labels nd. (Box 5)
- Series II: Photographs, 1865, ca. 1880-1986., Extent: 1.55 cu. ft. (5 boxes and 1 oversize folder). (Box 6-10)
  This series, 1865, ca. 1880-1986, includes numerous photographs of the Richmond Police Department, Alexander S. Wright, John M. Wright, and family and friends. Included are panoramic photographs of groups of policemen, dedication of the Richmond city building and Richmond Public Safety building, memorial service for fallen policemen, conventions and banquets, and various street scenes. Included are numerous publicity and portrait photographs of Alexander S. and John M. Wright. Also included are images of family, friends, vacations, and personal photographs.
  Arranged into two subseries: 1. Richmond Police Department Photographs; 2. Family Photographs.
  - Subseries 1: Richmond Police Department Photographs, ca. 1865-1969.
    - Banquets and meetings, ca. 1960-1969. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Groups of Policemen, ca. 1880-1960. (Box 6, Folder 2)
      (see also oversize photographs)
    - L.C. Hocke, 1963. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - International Association for Identification, 1946. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - International Police Conference (New York, NY), 12-16 May 1925. (Oversize Oversize folder)
      Panoramic photograph.
    - Memorial service for fallen policemen, 1965-1968. (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - National Police Week Convention (John Marshall Hotel, Richmond), 13-19 May 1962. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Office workers, ca. 1950-1960. (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Keith M. Pemberton meeting, 1965. (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Police academy and military parades, miscellaneous, ca. 1940-1950. (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Police on horseback, ca. 1950. (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Richmond after the Civil War, 1865. (Box 6, Folder 11)
      (Library of Congress reprints- duplication restricted)
    - Richmond City building, dedication, 1967. (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Richmond Police Department Reserve Officers and Safety Department Officials (Richmond, Va.), 25 June 1944. (Oversize Oversize folder)
      Panoramic photograph [LVA Lab# 10_1041_002]
    - Richmond Public Safety building, dedication, 1962. (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Street scenes, arrests, miscellaneous, ca. 1910-1950. (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Target practice, police, ca. 1940-1950. (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Virginia Association of Chiefs of Police Convention (Alexandria, Va.), 1929. (Oversize Oversize folder)
    - Virginia Association of Chiefs of Police Convention (John Marshall Hotel, Richmond), 1967. (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Virginia State F.O.P. Convention, 12 January 1964. (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Visiting police, 1960. (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Wright, John M., ca. 1930-1967. (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    - Wright, John M., Birthday celebration, 26 April 1962. (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Wright, John M. and Manchester Gang, ca. 1950-1964. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Wright, John M., Retirement dinner (Jefferson Hotel, Richmond), 1967. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Wright family: Alan S. Wright, Alexander S. Wright, Fred B. Wright, and John M. Wright. ca. 1900-1950. (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Oversize, ca. 1910-1960. (Box 8)
  - Subseries 2: Family and Personal Photographs, 1901-1986.
    - Family and friends, identified, 1919-1971. (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Houses and buildings, 1920-1968. (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Kahoun family, 1933. (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - May Day event [?], ca. 1945-1950. (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Travel, beach family vacation, ca. 1930-1965. (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Travel [DC, NY, VA], ca. 1950-1960. (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Wright, Frank A.S., ca. 1960. (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Wright, John M., 1901-1967. (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Unidentified children, ca. 1920-1970. (Box 9, Folder 9-10)
    - Unidentified studio portraits, 1927-1959. (Box 9, Folder 11-12)
    - Unidentified adults, ca. 1910-1940. (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Unidentified adults, ca. 1960-1986. (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Unidentified album, ca. 1920-1940. (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Negatives, ca. 1910-1950. (Box 10)
- Series III: Audio/Visual material, ca. 1968., Extent: .25 cu. ft. (1 box). (Box 10a)
  This series, ca. 1968, includes an audio CD of the retirement dinner for Colonel John M. Wright at the Hotel Jefferson, 12 January 1968. Also includes an unidentified film of Colonel John M. Wright at a police event.
  - Audio/visual materials, ca. 1968. (Box 10a)